A Finding Aid to the Robert Mills Family Letters, 1813-1847, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Robert Mills family letters
1813-1827
Archives of American Art
Mills Family
AAA.millfami
Archival Resource Key
0.2 Linear feet
This small collection of Robert Mills family letters date from 1813 to 1847 and measure 0.2 linear feet. Found here are 38 letters between architect Robert Mills and his wife Eliza, two letters to Mills from other family, and nine letters to Mills from business acquaintances, including architect John Skirving and engineer Louis Wernwag. Also found are six letters to Mills' daughter Anna from various family members.
Provenance
These letters were purchased from Robert S. Gamble of the Alabama Historical Society in 1985.
Related Material
Additional Robert Mills papers are available at the South Carolina Historical Society and the Library of Congress. Also available are the Records of the Robert Mills Paper Project at the Archives Center, National Museum of American History.
Alternative Forms Available
The letters of the Robert Mills Family in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2009, and total 187 images.
Restrictions on Access
Use of the original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Robert Mills (1781-1855) was born in 1781 in Charleston, South Carolina. As a teenager he studied pattern-books and learned the basics of drafting, and in 1800 he moved to Washington, DC, to work in the office of architect James Hoban. There he met President Thomas Jefferson who recommended Mills to Benjamin Latrobe. He was a pupil and assistant to Latrobe in Philadelphia until 1808, working on many architectural and engineering projects.
In 1808 Mills married Eliza Barnwell Smith and established his architectural practice in Philadelphia, receiving many major commissions. From 1815 to 1819 Mills lived with his family in Baltimore, Maryland, overseeing the construction of his commission for the Washington Monument in Baltimore. He also worked on several engineering projects in the city. After construction halted in 1819 due to an economic depression, he moved to South Carolina to become the Acting Commissioner of the Board of Public Works. In 1823 his position was abolished due to rising project costs, but he continued to work on individual commissions, and also published several books and pamphlets on South Carolina and engineering.
In 1830 Mills and his family moved to Washington, DC. There he directed alterations and restorations of the White House, Executive Offices, and the Capitol. After establishing himself with these projects he received many more commissions and was appointed Architect of the Federal Buildings. During this time his design for the Treasury Building was adopted, and he oversaw the construction of the U. S. Patent Office - now the Smithsonian Institution's Donald W. Reynolds Center for American Art and Portraiture - and the Old Post Office, among other projects. His federal office was abolished in 1842, but Mills continued to work on independent building projects. In 1845 his plan for the Washington Monument in Washington, DC, which he had designed in 1833, was adopted and construction began in 1848. He lived in Washington, DC, until his death in 1855.
Scope and Content Note
This small collection of Robert Mills family letters date from 1813 to 1847 and measure 0.2 linear feet. Found here are 38 letters between architect Robert Mills and his wife Eliza, the majority of which were written between 1813 and 1819, and generally discuss family news and health, his travels, finances, and their affection for each other. Also found are a fragment of a letter to Mills from his sister, Sarah, a letter to Mills from his mother-in-law, Ann Smith, and nine letters to Mills from business acquaintances, including architect John Skirving and engineer Louis Wernwag, regarding building projects. The collection also includes six letters to Mills' daughter Anna from her mother, Eliza, and cousins.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 1 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Robert Mills Family Letters, 1813-1847 (Box 1; 12 folders)
Architects -- Washington (D.C.); Architects -- Maryland -- Baltimore; Architects -- South Carolina; Mills, Robert, 1781-1855; Mills, Eliza Barnwell Smith, 1784-1865; Wernwag, Louis; Skirving, John
- Robert Mills Family Letters, 1813-1847; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 12 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are 38 letters between architect Robert Mills and his wife Eliza, the majority of which were written between 1813 and 1819, while Mills was working on projects in Baltimore and Richmond. These letters generally discuss family news and health, his travels, finances, and their affection for each other. Also found are a fragment of a letter to Mills from his sister, Sarah, a letter to Mills from his mother-in-law, Ann Smith, and nine letters to Mills from business acquaintances. Letters are from architect John Skirving and engineer Louis Wernwag and others. Wernwag's letter to Mills requests his help in finding work. Also of note is a letter from William Steuart regarding the commission of Steuart to do the marble work for the Washington Monument in Baltimore. The collection also includes six letters to Mills' daughter Anna from her mother, Eliza, and cousins.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged in chronological order.
  - Correspondence between Robert Mills and Eliza Barnwell Smith Mills, 1813; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between Robert Mills and Eliza Barnwell Smith Mills, 1813-1814; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence between Robert Mills and Eliza Barnwell Smith Mills, 1815-1817; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence between Robert Mills and Eliza Barnwell Smith Mills, 1818-1824; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence between Robert Mills and Eliza Barnwell Smith Mills, 1827-1830; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence between Robert Mills and Eliza Barnwell Smith Mills, Undated Letters, circa 1813-1830; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence between Robert Mills and Eliza Barnwell Smith Mills, Undated Letters, circa 1813-1830; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter to Robert Mills from his sister, Sarah, circa 1815; Archival Resource Key; (Letter Fragment) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter to Robert Mills from Ann Smith, circa 1815; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Robert Mills from John Skirving, 1840-1841; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Letters to Robert Mills, 1821-1847; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
    (Letters are from Mr. Butcher, Crocker Bros. & Co., Mitchell Hinmary?, Edward Stabler, William Steuart, and Louis Wernwag)
  - Miscellaneous Letters to Anna Mills, circa 1836-1841; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)